Boker tov בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody. Today's daf דף daf is
Ayin Beis עין ב, Ayin Beis, 72. We're in the middle of
the eighth perek פרק perek and there are short dappim דפים dappim
because there are huge Tosafos תוספות. Tosafos. I will try to give
you a sense of what some of the Tosafos תוספות Tosafos are
about.
Some of the—the big one from yesterday's daf דף, daf, from Shabbos's
שבת Shabbos's daf דף daf actually is more relevant to a discussion
we're going to get to tomorrow, so I'll hold off relating to
it tomorrow. Anyway, but today we're in the middle of the—the perek
פרק perek introduced the idea that if one—if one animal that is
forbidden in hana'ah הנאה, hana'ah, like a shor haniskal שור הנסקל, shor
haniskal, an animal that's supposed to be stoned, or chatas hameisos חטאת
המיתות, chatas hameisos, a chatas חטאת chatas that you have to let
die, gets mixed up with a group of sacrifices, none of them
can be brought as sacrifices and none of them you can derive
benefit because you have to—it's not battel בטל battel and you have
to assume everything is a thing that is forbidden in benefit. So
basically, you have to just let them all die.
And that's—and if it's an animal that is forbidden as a sacrifice
but not forbidden to derive benefit, like let's say it's a—something that's
a treifah טריפה treifah or something like that was born as a
Caesarean section, then you don't have to let them die, but you
can't bring any of them as sacrifices. And the Mishnah משנה Mishnah
discusses how you wait for them to get a blemish and redeem
their value and so on. Okay, but the basic principle of all
of these things is that they're not battel בטל, battel, even if
the Mishnah משנה Mishnah says one in ten thousand, you know, even
bechol shehu בכל שהוא. bechol shehu. So the question is: why not?
Whatever happened to the laws of bitul ביטול? bitul? So that's what
we're going to turn to right now. So top of—or whatever, very
big bottom, middle of Ayin Beis Amud Aleph עין ב עמוד א,
Ayin Beis Amud Aleph, within the eight lines of Ayin Beis Amud
Aleph עין ב עמוד א. Ayin Beis Amud Aleph. Okay, so the
Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this: Venivtelu berova וניבטלו ברובא. Venivtelu berova.
It is five lines—six lines down. Berova ברובא. Berova. Let it—let it
taka טאקע taka be battel berov בטל ברוב, battel berov, okay? Why
isn't it battel berov בטל ברוב? battel berov? Now, rov רוב rov
is an interesting question. Sometimes we have a number of 60 or
100 or 200.
Sometimes Rishonim ראשונים Rishonim say that sometimes when the Gemara גמרא Gemara
says let it be battel berov בטל ברוב, battel berov, it doesn't
specifically mean rov רוב, rov, but it just means let it be
battel בטל, battel, whatever the number is that you want to pick,
let it be battel בטל. battel. One minute. So, why isn't this
battel בטל? battel? Vechi teima chashiv velo batil וכי תימא חשיב ולא
בטיל. Vechi teima chashiv velo batil. If you say: 'Well, it's a—like
a big cow, that's important, and that's not battel בטל.' battel. Okay,
so now—hani nicha leman de'amar kol shedarko limanos shoninu הניחא למאן דאמר
כל שדרכו למנות שנינו. hani nicha leman de'amar kol shedarko limanos shoninu.
That's good according to the one that says it in a Mishnah
משנה Mishnah where we discuss important things that are not battel בטל.
battel. The phrase used, the—the way to conceptualize what is it that
is important that's not battel בטל, battel, is anything that is normally
counted. Ela
leman de'amar es shedarko limanos shoninu אלא למאן דאמר את שדרכו למנות
שנינו, Ela leman de'amar es shedarko limanos shoninu, but if the phrase
in the Mishnah משנה Mishnah is not kol shedarko limanos כל שדרכו
למנות, kol shedarko limanos, anything that is normally, naturally counted, but es
shedarko limanos את שדרכו למנות, es shedarko limanos, only those things that
are counted,
meaning—I'll say the difference in a minute—then mai ika lemeimar מאי איכא
למימר, mai ika lemeimar, then what can you say? Now what is
the difference between kol shedarko limanos כל שדרכו למנות kol shedarko limanos
and es shedarko limanos את שדרכו למנות? es shedarko limanos? So kol
shedarko limanos כל שדרכו למנות kol shedarko limanos means things that are,
you know, some—it's very natural to count them, but you don't always
count them, like tomatoes.
You might buy them by the pound, or you might buy a
tomato.
Very good. You might buy a—they sell tomatoes by the individual tomato?
Yeah. Okay. Yeah, where do they sell tomatoes by the individual tomato?
You want to go to maybe—what?
Oh,
that's always by the pound. Okay, I don't know what store you
go to.
No, no, no, I don't mean whether you buy them. I mean
how do you pay for them? If you say, 'Oh, we're selling
so-so tomatoes,' isn't it going to be—a watermelon is an example. Watermelon
is an example. Okay, bananas are an example. Okay, so sometimes you
buy bananas, you know, especially if you buy them on the street,
four for a dollar, whatever it is. Okay, whereas if you buy
them in the store, you say they sell them by the pound.
Bana—watermelons. Okay, watermelons is often five dollars for a whole watermelon or
you buy it by the pound. Okay, so something like that. Now,
so sometimes it's—so what's the idea? The idea—that's something that's kol shedarko
limanos כל שדרכו למנות. kol shedarko limanos. It's natural to sell it
by the number, but it's also natural to sell it in other
ways as well. Es shedarko limanos את שדרכו למנות Es shedarko limanos
are things that are only sold by number, not sold by any
other measure. For example,
cars.
Okay, or—yeah. Now, it's interesting, you could say—'cause it's not always about
the cost of something. You know, you could say like eggs.
Okay, 'cause you never buy eggs by weight. Okay, but Rashi רש"י
Rashi says that eggs would not be a good example, well, in
the—you know, in the time of the Rishonim ראשונים, Rishonim, eggs wouldn't
be a good example because you would sell a basket of eggs
and it wouldn't be based on a certain—per number. Or you might
sell a dozen but throw in an extra one, a farmer's dozen
they used to call it. I'm just teasing, anyway. But Rashi רש"י
Rashi says you would throw in an extra. What would be other
things that you would only buy by
the—by the unit?
Bagels—bagels you don't go by weight.
No—well, watermelon you could—typically a house you'd—well, obviously. Anyway, but the thing
is, it depends, if you're like in a big fund and you're
buying like a whole bunch of them, you may negotiate.
You can negotiate, but it doesn't—that's a little different. Anyway, so what's
the— The logic is as you could see, it's not all about
cost, okay? What it's about is the following, if we want to
say something is not בטל, batel, okay, if you have like things
and each one of it has its own significance and its own
importance, so then it can't lose its identity in the mass. Part
of the concept of how we say ביטול, bitul, now this is
of course a whole debate when we speak about יבש ביבש yavesh
b'yavesh how it works, but in general the consensus is that ביטול
bitul of יבש ביבש yavesh b'yavesh means discrete items, works somewhat similar
to the way it works when it's לח בלח, lach b'lach, like
if you drop a drop of blood into a, you know, into
a pot of chicken soup. So when you have a drop of
blood that goes into a pot of chicken soup and it's, you
know, a tiny amount, we say, well, it loses its identity. There's
like there's no blood there. That's normally how we say לח בלח
lach b'lach works. If we say, right here, let's talk about iPads,
iPhones, iPhones are not things you sell by weight, okay? So if
we say, you know, you've got your various iPhones here, okay, this
is a Samsung anyway, you got, let's assume these are all iPhones,
okay, so it's not, so it's harder to say, you know, this
which is the problematic iPhone as it were, the problematic cow, it's
like it doesn't even exist. It's one thing to say a piece,
a drop of blood that fully disperses into a whole pot of
chicken soup, you know, and you there's no specific concrete presence of
it and it's only trace amounts, it's like it doesn't exist. This
is harder. But nevertheless, according to most ראשונים rishonim in the end
of the day, that's the logic of how this works. It's like
if there's a whole group of them, so if you think about
like, you know,
if you think about like if there's a whole, I don't know,
let's talk about tomatoes. You've got a hundred tomatoes and one of
them is, you know, some problematic כלאיים kilayim or something like that,
it's like okay, you know, it's just like there's like a lot
of tomatoes here and the one that's a problem because you look
at it as a whole group, you don't look at them as
distinct units. Because you look at the whole group, there is one
problematic thing, but because it's part of a larger group and we
can't find the problematic one, it's like that problematic one stops existing,
okay? It's overwhelmed by the numbers, you know, by the numbers of
the rest. You know that big poster that they have about like
this island full of penguins and there's, you know, they're all exactly
the same and there's one little penguin just saying I just gotta
be me or something like that? So that doesn't work. No, I
just gotta be me, okay? So like, you know, so everybody, you
get lost in the masses, okay, and therefore you stop, it stops
existing. That's the logic.
But that's when you just look at it as this, you know,
amorphous collection of kind of little things, no one has a distinct
identity. Okay, so you look at a big yard full of, you
know, like a car lot and you know and every single car
there is whatever, you see a lot of cars, but don't tell
me any one particular car, you know, each one has its own
weight and importance and therefore even if there's a hundred of them,
it's not like the one particular one should, as if it were,
lose its identity. So the way it's determined that is well, if
you only sell them by the unit, it means that you give
individual weight to each particular one. Okay, that's את שדרכו לימנות, et
shedarko limanot, you only sell it by the unit. You never see
it as just, you know, you know, just adding weight to the
sum total. You know, it's, you know, each one is always seen
separately and that's את שדרכו לימנות et shedarko limanot and therefore you
don't say בטל batel because each, you look at each one separately
and independently. כל שדרכו
לימנות kol shedarko limanot has a lower threshold, you know, to prevent
בטל. batel. It says since you sometimes look at it independently and
separately, since you sometimes count watermelons separately, if you have a hundred
watermelons, I don't just think I have a thousand pounds of watermelons
here, right, because I actually always will say I got a hundred
distinct watermelons because sometimes you sell them separately. That is enough to
say that you continue to look at each one distinct, and if
you continue to look at each one distinct, it's not part of
some large collection, it's each one, you know, is a separate and
independent unit, okay? So you know that's my sort of normal ווארט
vort about why we don't count people and we only count money.
Because you can like, you can, you know, you can sort of
amass, what's the word I'm looking for? But anyway, you can like
sum money. You can't sum people, right? One, two, three, four, there
are four people here, that means that in principle each one of
you is interchangeable and you just sort of gather together to make
some number, whereas no, Michael is always Michael, you know, David is
always David, Hanan is always Hanan, there's no way we can just
amass you into some number. Charlie doesn't count.
Charlie just adds to the number.
Anyway, but anyway, so that's the idea, right? If something always retains
its distinct identity, you don't just get to sort of like collect,
you know, see it as part of a collection without seeing it
distinct. That's the question of את שדרכו לימנות et shedarko limanot and
כל שדרכו לימנות, kol shedarko limanot, but the logic is the same.
When you count them individually, okay, and you always sort of count
the number and not some larger weight or larger mass of them,
then it doesn't become just lost in the mass and become בטל.
batel. And therefore it's there's no ביטול. bitul. Yes?
So three things: one, I just want to point out some of
their tomatoes are sold by volume, some by weight, and some by
count. Okay. Second, in terms of an individual is problematic, there's a
famous ישיבה Yeshiva picture with one guy in the blue shirt.
Okay, there we go.
That's probably me. Third, the question I was going to ask about
the ביטול ברוב. bitul berov. A lot of these times where we
talk about ביטול בשישים bitul beshishim or whatever, בשישים beshishim or something,
is it, don't we often say that the תורה Torah הלכה halacha
would be would be ביטול ברוב? bitul berov? But the... Yes. Yes.
Except it could be by things of מין במינו min bemino or
לח בלח. lach belach. Not that way, but in general, yes. And
that could be why you use the phrase רוב, rov, because even
if the end number we end up with is different than just
a majority, the principle starts with the תורה Torah concept of רוב,
rov, even if the rabbis change the number. Yes, that's a good...
yes, thank you for pointing that out. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara wants to say, okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara wants to say, okay, says the גמרא, Gemara, so why is
it not בטל? batel? Oh, because an animal, a cow, is important.
So the גמרא Gemara says, well, that's only if you say כל
שדרכו לימנות. kol shedarko limanot. For sometimes you sell cows by the
number. Okay, how many head of cattle do you have? But if
you say
את שדרכו... et shedarko... but you don't always sell them by the
number. And when do you not always... okay, put it away.
When do you not sell cattle by the number? So רש״י Rashi
says, well, like Michael said, sometimes you just buy a herd of
cattle or a flock of sheep and you don't count them. I
don't know, I'm not a farmer, it's hard for me to imagine
that because, but maybe, okay, or so... so that's what רש״י Rashi
says. Now תוספות, Tosafot, so therefore that's what the גמרא Gemara says:
if you say it's something that's only counted, cattle doesn't fall into
that. Cattle is sometimes sold as part of a herd. If you
say it's something that's generally counted, then cattle would fall and that
would explain why some... but one of the unique תוספותים Tosafots in
here is to say, give me a break. What תוספות Tosafot basically
said is I don't care if you say את שדרכו לימנות et
shedarko limanot or כל שדרכו לימנות. kol shedarko limanot. A head of
cattle is independently important. I mean, you're going to see the things
that are in this category are things that are important. And תוספות
Tosafot said, cattle is has got to be at least as independently
important as all these other things. And תוספות Tosafot doesn't really understand
how the גמרא Gemara feels it's part of this debate. So he
doesn't really come up with a satisfying answer, but at least he
puts the question out there which is the natural thing to ask.
Like even if sometimes you sell a herd of cattle, you got
a cow like that's that has a lot of independent weight. So...
yes, like your car example. What?
Oh, it would be like your car example.
Right. So let's take a look at the גמרא, Gemara, okay? So
דתנן. d'tnan.
Now where do we see this debate of whether it's את שדרכו
לימנות et shedarko limanot or כל שדרכו לימנות? kol shedarko limanot?
This comes up a couple of times in ש״ס. Shas.
Always. Okay.
מי שהיו לו כבילי תילסן. mi shehayu lo kavlei tilson. Somebody had
bundles of fenugreek.
של כלאי הכרם shel kilay hakerem and they were כלאים. kilayim.
Exactly, yes. So you pick a head of cattle is at least
as important as a bundle of fenugreek. ידלקו. yidalku. So you have
to burn it. You have to destroy it because it's כלאים. kilayim.
נתערבו באחרים. nitarevu b'acherim. If it gets mixed up with others. And
there's a question of if you have this גרסא girsa באחר באחרים,
b'acher b'acherim, meaning you have one gets mixed up with 100, then
one out of that 100 comes and gets mixed up with another
100. Do you say the second
100 that it's all ספק ספיקא sfek sfeka or is that only
something you say by עבודה זרה? avoda zara? So that's the question
that... that's another one of the big תוספותים. Tosafots. Whether you have
that גרסא girsa באחר באחרים. b'acher b'acherim. Okay. Anyway, כולן ידלקו. kulan
yidalku.
So if one gets mixed up, even in like 10,000, it all
gets destroyed. Okay. תו. tu. Okay. So now דברי רבי מאיר. divrei
Rabbi Meir. Now so that's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that it's
בכל-שה. be-kol-she. וחכמים אומרים יעלו באחד ומאתים. vachachamim omrim ya'alu b'echad umatayim.
No,
it's בטל batel in 200. Okay. כלאים kilayim is 200. תרומה terumah
is 100. כלאים, kilayim, which is more forbidden, it's forbidden in הנאה,
hana'ah, is 200. תרומה terumah 100 because basically there's a type of
a תרומה, terumah, תרומת מעשר, terumat ma'aser, which is one-tenth of the
לוי's Levi tenth, which is one in 100. So if you have
100 against the תרומה, terumah, it's בטל. batel. Anyway, because the תרומה
terumah is one...
but it's 200 for
the normal proportion is that there's one could be one unit of
תרומת מעשר terumat ma'aser against 99 units of grain. Hard to understand,
right? So anyway, so therefore... what? שמאה sheme'ah is 100 is בטל?
batel? So so כלאים kilayim is 200.
Is that like an arbitrary number, 200?
Yeah, it's just doubled. It's more אסור, assur, so we're going to
double it. Okay. שהיה רבי מאיר אומר, shehaya Rabbi Meir omer, because
because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir used to say... now, רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir normally agrees that כלאים kilayim is בטל batel in 200. Why
is he making... why is he saying here it's not בטל? batel?
Because he used to say כל שדרכו לימנות. kol shedarko limanot. Look
at the side, it's hilarious. Of the right-hand side, it says some
have the גרסא girsa את שדרכו לימנות. et shedarko limanot. Like no
kidding, that's going to be the debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. The question is like what is the...
the debate is what is the נוסח nusach in the משנה. Mishnah.
Okay. But the question is I guess when the גמרא Gemara initially
quotes it, does it quote it with the כל kol or does
it quote it with the את? et? So anyway, our version initially
quotes it with the כל. kol. Anything that's normally counted,
מקדש, mekadesh, sanctifies, like פנכא דמליא עדשים. pincha d'malya adashim. thing of
saying permitted to make everything forbidden. So since normally it's a natural
thing to sell fenugreek by the number, therefore, it's not
בטל. battel. חכמים Chachamim say אינו מקדש אלא שישה דברים בלבד. eino
mekadesh ela shisha devarim bilvad. Only six things, nothing else. Those are
so important that they're not בטל. battel. They reject the whole idea
that there's a general principle of things normally counted. Even things normally
counted are בטל. battel. Only six things are so important that they're
not בטל. battel. רבי עקיבא אומר שבעה. Rabbi Akiva omer shiva. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says seven. ואלו הן, ve'elu hein, and here they
are: אגוזי פרך, Egozei Prach, those nuts from this place called פרך;
Prach; רימוני בדן, Rimonei Bedan, pomegranates from בדן; Bedan; וחביות סתומות, ve'chaviyot
stumot, sealed barrels of wine; וקלחי תרדין, ve'kilchei tardin, and some type
of bunches of beets; וקלחי כרוב, ve'kilchei krov, and also like heads
of cabbage; ודלעת יונית, ve'dila'at yevanit, and a Greek gourd. Okay, and
that's six. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva מוסיף אף קיכרות של בעל הבית,
mosif af kikarot shel ba'al habayit, freshly baked home-baked bread. הראוי לערלה
ערלה, ha're'ui le'orla orla, some of these things are fruit therefore they
would fall in the
ערלה Orla category; והראוי לכלאים כלאים, ve'ha're'ui le'kilayim kilayim, some of these
things would be כלאים. Kilayim. Fine. Okay, so therefore you have the
חכמים Chachamim and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva saying we don't even hold
this את שדרכו כל שדרכו. et she'darco kol she'darco. They only have
like six or seven things.
תוספות Tosafot was saying,
I feel even according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the חכמים,
Chachamim, a head of cattle is about as important as a loaf
of bread. Why wasn't it mentioned? I guess it's pretty obvious. Why?
I know. So that's תוספות, Tosafot, that's what that big תוספות Tosafot
is about. Doesn't understand the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. What do you mean
את שדרכו כל שדרכו? et she'darco kol she'darco? Give me a break,
okay? You have... I'm guessing that a pomegranate from בדן Bedan is
not as important as a head of cattle, okay? Even if
it's a question
about... you look at it as a separate unit or not. All
right. You know if you have a box full of בדן Bedan
pomegranates and you have a herd full of cattle, I guess is
you look at each
individual cow more separately than you look at each individual pomegranate in
a box full of these בדן Bedan pomegranates.
Why is the list only restricted to these seven?
The רמב"ן Ramban says it's not just these seven. He says these
are anything that would be of similar importance. But you can't abstract
it so much to the point that anything normally counted. You normally
count eggs, right? So the רמב"ם, Rambam, this is like a similar
idea, but רמב"ם Rambam just says it's more contextual. You have to
really feel that this thing is weighty. It's not just that it
technically falls into the category of something normally counted. Okay, so you
have a category that's just is it normally counted or is it
only counted. You know that's the first position. The second position is
only things that are very weighty. All right. And the גמרא Gemara
somehow feels that cattle makes only like the lowest threshold which is
strange. תוספות Tosafot says satisfy even highest criteria. Anyway,
גמרא Gemara says like this: ואיתמר עלן, ve'itmar alan, was said on
this; רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan had
explaining רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's position: את דרכו למנות שנינו. et darco
limnot shinan tanu. The right version of the משנה Mishnah is things
that are only counted. That's the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir position, the
broader one. וריש לקיש אמר, ve'Reish Lakish amar, כל דרכו למנות שנינו.
kol darco limnot shinan tanu. Things that are generally counted.
Okay. הא ניחא לשיטת ריש לקיש, ha nicha leshitat Reish Lakish, we
understand why cattle isn't בטל battel because it's in this כל שדרכו
kol she'darco category. Okay. אלא לרבי יוחנן מאי איכא למימר, ela le'Rabbi
Yochanan mai ikka le'meimar, what can you say for רבי יוחנן? Rabbi
Yochanan? And again as we've now said five times, okay, it would
seem to me even for רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan cattle would count,
but okay, the גמרא Gemara is not going to go there. תוספות
Tosafot actually has another question, another one of the big תוספותים. Tosafotim.
Wants to know there's another principle which is that a בריה biryah
is not בטל. battel. Something that's a whole unit. Why isn't a
cow a whole unit? So תוספות Tosafot says the concept of בריה
biryah does not just mean... what makes something a בריה? biryah? So
תוספות Tosafot has this whole fascinating discussion what constitutes a בריה. biryah.
תוספות Tosafot basically says what makes something a בריה biryah is that
it is the object that the תורה Torah has described as forbidden.
So what does that mean? When the תורה Torah says don't eat
a גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh, so a גיד הנשה gid hanasheh is
the בריה. biryah. So even if you ate let's... because the תורה
Torah identifies that as the forbidden thing,
even if it was less than a כזית, kezayit, you get lashes,
it's not בטל battel because that is the object the תורה Torah
has forbidden. Or it says don't eat any flying insect, and you
eat a flying insect that's tiny or whatever, you get lashes even
though it's less than a כזית kezayit because that's exactly the thing
the תורה Torah said. And if you have them mixed up or
whatever, it's not בטל battel because it is the thing the תורה
Torah has identified and it's weighty. And here, when I've got this
cow that's a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, the תורה Torah actually says
don't eat the meat of a שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. So the
תורה Torah never identified the cow as the forbidden thing. Okay. And
because of that even though it's big and whatever, because it's not
the unit that is described as the unit that is forbidden, the
תורה Torah says don't eat from the meat of, so there's just
a lot of meat put together as it were, it's not significant
as the cow, therefore it does not fall into the בריה biryah
category. Okay, so that's interesting. It could be big and alive and
whatever, and the גיד הנשה gid hanasheh in it could be a
בריה, biryah, but the thing itself is not a בריה biryah because
of the perspective of what makes it forbidden. It's not forbidden qua
cattle, right, it's forbidden as don't eat from the meat of. Okay.
Therefore there's no weight to the whole unit of the cow. Did
you hear, people, sort of?
Okay, but you said it can be anything.
Right, can be anything. So why wouldn't it just say something
else? You can, well that's what we're looking for, the something else.
One thing we tried to do is דרכי למונות darkei lemonot and
the גמרא Gemara for whatever reason thought it fell into the כל
שדרכו לימנות kol she-darko li-manot category. So תוספות Tosafot says well what
about the בריה biryah principle? Because a בריה, biryah, a unit, okay
which is another way of saying unit, is לא בטיל. lo batil.
And so it says that concept of בריה biryah only applies when
that is the unit that the תורה Torah has made forbidden. The
תורה's Torah identified that as the problematic. Okay?
But yeah, we're trying to look for other reasons why this cow
is significant. Alright, so let's keep on going. So now, it's not
enough significant to say it's counted because it's not only exclusively counted.
Again, strange idea, but that's what the גמרא's Gemara saying, okay? It's
not weighty enough to fall into that category. So now the גמרא
Gemara says אמר רב פפא האי תנא תנא דליטרא קציעות הוא. Amar
Rav Papa hai tana tana de-litra ketziot hu. Our תנא tana that
feels that a cow is בטל batel is the תנא tana of
this discussion about a ליטרא litra of pressed figs, okay, that says,
דאמר de-amar who says, and we're going to quote this משנה Mishnah
in a minute, who says כל דבר שיש בו מניין אפילו בדרבנן
לא בטיל. kol davar she-yesh bo minyan afilu be-drabbanan lo batil. Meaning
anything, it's sort of like the את כל שדרכו לימנות et kol
she-darko li-manot of the גמרא, Gemara, anything that is sometimes counted is
not בטל, batel, meaning whatever the position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is, that maybe according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says את שדרכו
לימנות. et she-darko li-manot. It's only something that's exclusively counted. But he's
going to say I will show you the author of a משנה
Mishnah that reflects the position of כל שדרכו לימנות, kol she-darko li-manot,
that even something that is sometimes counted is not בטל. batel. And
he even says it by something that's only forbidden rabbinically. Okay? So
the גמרא Gemara says, you got it? The גמרא Gemara says wait,
this cow is not exclusively counted, it's only sometimes counted, so that
might not fit into רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir because there's a debate
what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said. Does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say
exclusively or sometimes counted? So comes along רב פפא Rav Papa and
says, okay fine, whatever רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said, I will show
you a תנא tana that says even if it's sometimes counted it's
not בטל, batel, and that could explain our משנה. Mishnah. And this
תנא tana says it even by something that's only forbidden rabbinically, and
certainly something that is biblically forbidden. So which means then that כל
שכן דאורייתא, kol she-ken de-Oraita, certainly something that's biblically forbidden. Yes, okay,
so it means that basically what we're saying at
this point is there could be some disagreement with our משנה Mishnah
potentially.
Yeah, if you say if it's based on this principle of כל
שדרכו, kol she-darko, את שדרכו et she-darko etc. according to the גמרא
Gemara already said implicitly רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the חכמים Chachamim
disagree with our משנה, Mishnah, because they only they only say it
by בדן Bedan pomegranates, they wouldn't say it by that. Okay? But
again, we're going to we're going to, don't worry, we're going to
get to a position where everybody's going to be on our משנה.
Mishnah. Because give me a break, it's a cow, okay? So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now, what
is this what is this תנא? tana? דתניא, de-tanya, we learned in
a ברייתא. beraita. Okay? ליטרא קציעות. Litra ketziot. You've got a there's
a question whether it's דתנן de-tenan or דתניא de-tanya because there's a
משנה Mishnah that sounds like it, but this is probably a ברייתא
beraita variation of the משנה. Mishnah. ליטרא קציעות. Litra ketziot. You have
a ליטרא, litra, whatever it's the same thing, yeah
right רש"י Rashi says it's a ליטרא's litra a weight,
I assume, it's a I'm gonna call it a ליטרא. litra. Steinsaltz
says it's also a weight. Yeah, okay. You have a I guess
ליטרא's litra a volume. Alright, fine, whatever. You got a pound of
these of these pressed figs. שדרסה על פי עיגול, she-darsa al pi
igul, and you pressed them by a round, like what they would
do is they would basically get a barrel, right? And רש"י Rashi
sort of says this is also how you would make rounds of
cheese, okay? You'd get a barrel, you'd put in all of the
all of the dates, you'd stomp on them or whatever, and then
you know because it's in a barrel it would become like a
pressed round of dates, and then you would keep on doing it
with the next one, and then you would sort of get, you
know, this whole big column or whatever, you know, cylinder of pressed
dates, and then presumably you'd just like, you know, peel off the
top layer or cut off the top layer like you would do
with like a round of cheese, okay? And that's what you would
do. So you went ahead and you stomped. Okay? Now, שדרסה על
פי עיגול ואיני יודע באיזה עיגול דרסה. she-darsa al pi igul ve-eini
yodeia be-eizeh igul darsa. Now, this here is some some תרומה, trumah,
okay? And you don't know so תרומה's trumah only בטל batel in
a hundred. Here you've got you've put in, you've got a hundred
barrels, all these barrels, okay? And you know in one of these
barrels the top layer is תרומה trumah dates that I stomped. And
I only the top layer, only the top layer, and I don't
remember which barrel it was. Okay? So. ואיני יודע באיזה חבית דרסה
באיזה עיגול דרסה. ve-eini yodeia be-eizeh chavit darsa be-eizeh igul darsa. You
don't know in which round, על פי חבית, al pi chavit, or
it was at the head of a barrel, and עיגול igul is
a different type of a circular vessel, or a barrel. ואיני יודע
באיזה חבית דרסה. ve-eini yodeia be-eizeh chavit darsa. You don't know what
barrel. על פי כוורת. al pi kaveret. כוורת Kaveret literally a beehive,
but again is a type of a vessel that looks like a
beehive. All these are sort of cylindrical circular vessels. ואיני יודע באיזה
כוורת דרסה. ve-eini yodeia be-eizeh kaveret darsa. Fine. רבי מאיר אומר. Rabbi
Meir omer. Now, רבי מאיר... Rabbi Meir... Everybody knew it was a
debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, but
they debated what the debate was. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said,
here was the debate. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer Omer, רואין אותה
כאילו הן פרודות Roein Oso K'ilu Hein Perudot והתחתונה מעלות על העליונה.
v'Hatahtona Maalot al Haelyona. You look at the top layer as if
they're separate. Okay? Now separate, but it's a funny way of saying
it. What it means is, you look at it as if it's
separate and mixed up. So therefore you need 100. Everybody agrees you
need 100. But do you need 100 top layers or 100 barrels?
Because the only doubt is which of the top layers it is.
So it comes along in this and this is a very lenient
approach and this says, no, you look at it as if it's
separate from the top and mixed in, and therefore you only need
100 times, you know, that, that. Understand the separate but mixed in.
If they're separate, then they're not mixed in.
I know, but somehow, no, if it's in its fixed place and
it's fixed, then it's fixed at the top. If it's free floating,
it could, you know, theoretically be anywhere. That seems to be the
point. So therefore, you only need 100, so you if there's a
big barrel has 50 of these, you'd only need two barrels to
do that. Okay? You only, you look at all of the pressed
figs and that creates the 100. That's that opinion. רבי יהושע אומר,
Rabbi Yehoshua Omer, that's רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir version of רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says, no, you only focus, you
look at each top layer and only on each top layer. אם
יש מאה פומים יעלו Im Yesh Meiah Pumim Yaalu if there are
100 of the other barrels then it's בטל, Battel, ואם לאו v'Im
Lav and if not, הפומים אסורים והשוליים מותרים, HaPumim Assurim v'Hashulayim Muttarim,
everything on the top layer of every barrel is forbidden, you know,
or it's a mixture of תרומה Terumah and חולין. Chullin. A כהן
Kohen could eat it. Okay? But everything below the top layer is
permitted because the doubt isn't in the bottom in the, is not
below the top layer, the doubts are only in the top layer.
That's, that's רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir version of the debate. רבי יהודה
אומר, Rabbi Yehuda Omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, רבי אליעזר אומר,
Rabbi Eliezer Omer, אם יש שם ק' פומים יעלו, Im Yesh Sham
Kuf Pumim Yaalu, אם לאו הפומים אסורים. Im Lav HaPumim Assurim. So
he has everybody being one step more strict. Okay? רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says you look at the mouths of the barrels and you
need 100 mouths. Okay? So that's a reasonable position. Now how is
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua going to make it even stricter than that?
So רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua Omer, אפילו יש שם שלוש מאות
פומים לא יעלו. Afilu Yesh Sham Shlosha Meiot Pumim Lo Yaalu. I
don't care if there's 300 barrels. Why? Because, okay, why? Because this
is דבר שדרכו לימנות. Davar she'darko limnos. Because since you sometimes sell
the rounds by number, so he basically says a round is something
that is normally counted and therefore it's not בטל. Battel. So here
you've got רבי, Rabbi, according to רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda version of
רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, it's something that's only Rabbinic because תרומה Terumah
by fruit is Rabbinic or תרומה בזמן הזה Terumah Bizman HaZeh is
Rabbinic or both or whatever. And it's only Rabbinic and it's only
something that is כל שדרכו לימנות, Kol she'darko limnos, just you know
כל דבר שיש בו מניין, Kol davar she'yesh bo minyan, it's sometimes
counted or whatever, and nevertheless it's not בטל. Battel. Okay? Now the
last line of this ברייתא Braita is, okay, דרסה בעיגול ואינו יודע
באיזה מקום בעיגול דרסה, אם לצפון אם לדרום. Darsa b'igul v'eino yodea
b'eizeh makom b'igul darsa, im l'tzafon im l'darom. If it doesn't have
a distinct place, it's just somewhere in the barrel, in that case,
דברי הכל יעלו, Divrei Hakol Yaalu, everybody agrees it's not a distinct
unit, it's just smooshed with everything else. It's just, you know, and
it doesn't have a ספירה Sfira here, it's got a ספירה, Sfira,
it might be דבר שדרכו לימנות Davar she'darko limnos because it's a
specific thing and you would cut it off and you sell that
separate. But if it's just like if, if the things are mixed
up in the whole barrel then fine, then everybody agrees it's בטל.
Battel. Anyway, so that's right now our answer. Our answer is why
is the cow not בטל? Battel? Because it is something that is
counted. And though the גמרא Gemara says it's not so special like
again, this is ironic, like the pomegranates of ברדן Bardan and it's
not something that's only exclusively counted, but according to those opinions that
you go by things that are sometimes counted, that's why the cow
is not בטל. Battel. Now we're going to,
that seems to make it, as Michael pointed out, only the opinion
of some תנאים. Tannaim. Now we're going to get to another explanation
which is more basic, which is, and which
is הלכה, Halacha, actually. Okay. גמרא אומר, Gemara Omer, רבא אמר אפילו
תימא רבנן, Rava Amar Afilu Teima Rabbanan, even the Rabbis who argue
and say אפשר דרכו לימנות Efshar darko limnos or you need the
רימוני ברדן Rimonei Bardan and only the six or seven things, בעלי
חיים חשימי ולא בטלי. Ba'alei chayim chashimi v'lo batli. Something that is
a living thing is important and it doesn't lose its identity, like
my point before about counting, you know, not counting people, only counting
objects. You only, objects can be like, it can be sort of
like, amassed or whatever. There's a better word for that. Anyway.